CONTRARY Mary had liked to look at her mother from a distance and she had
thought her very pretty, but as she knew very little of her she could scarcely
have been expected to love her or to miss her very much when she was
gone. She did not miss her at all, in fact, and as she was a self-absorbed child she
gave her entire thought to herself, as she had always
done. If she had been older she would no doubt have been very anxious at being
left alone in the world, but she was very young, and as she had always been taken
care of, she supposed she always would be.
What she thought was that she would like to know if she was going to nice people,
who would be polite to her and give her her own way as her a and the other
native servants had done. She knew that she was not going to
stay at the English clergyman's house where she was taken at first. She did not want to
stay. The English clergyman was poor and he had five children nearly all the same
age and they wore shabby clothes and were always quarreling and snatching
toys from each other. Mary hated their untidy bungalow and was so disagreeable
to them that after the first day or two nobody would play with
her. By the second day they had given her a nickname which made her
furious. It was Basil who thought of it first. Basil was a little boy with
impudent blue eyes and a Turned Up nose and Mary hated him. She was playing by
herself under a tree, just as she had been playing the day the Cera broke
out. She was making heaps of earth and paths for a garden and Basil came and
stood near to watch her. Presently he got rather interested and suddenly made a
suggestion. "Why don't you put a heap of stones there and pretend it is a rockery?"
he said. "There in the middle," and he leaned over her to point. "Go away!" cried
Mary. "I don't want boys. Go away!" For a moment Basil looked angry, and
then he began to tease.
He was always teasing his sisters. He danced round and around her and made
faces and sang and laughed. "Mistress Mary, quite contrary, How does your garden grow?
With silver bells, and cockle shells, And marigolds all in a
row." He sang it until the other children heard and laughed, too; and the crosser
Mary got, the more they sang "Mistress Mary, quite contrary"; and after that as long as she
stayed with them they called her "Mistress Mary Quite Contrary" when they
spoke of her to each other, and often when they spoke to her. "You are going to
be sent home," Basil said to her, "at the
end of the week. And we're glad of it." "I
am glad of it, too," answered Mary. "Where is home?" "She doesn't know where home is!" said
Basil, with seven-year-old scorn. "It's England, of course.
Our grandmama lives there and our sister Mabel was sent to her last year. You are
not going to your grandmama. You have none. You are going to your uncle. His
name is Mr archeal Craven." "I don't know anything about him," snapped Mary. "I know
you don't," Basil answered. "You don't know anything. Girls never do. I heard father
and mother talking about him. He lives in a great, big, desolate old house in the
country and no one goes near him. He's so cross he won't let them, and they
wouldn't come if he would let them. He's a hunchback, and he's
horrid." "I don't believe you," said Mary; and she turned her back and stuck her
fingers in her ears, because she would not listen anymore But she thought over it a great
deal afterward; and when Mrs. Crawford told her that night that she was going
to sail away to England in a few days and go to her uncle, Mr archal Craven,
who lived at mle Manor, she looked so stony and stubbornly uninterested that
they did not know what to think about her. They tried to be kind to her, but she
only turned her face away when Mrs.
Crawford attempted to kiss her, and held herself stiffly when Mr. Crawford patted her
shoulder. "She is such a plain child," Mrs.
Crawford said pityingly, afterward. "And her mother was such a pretty creature.
She had a very pretty manner, too, and Mary has the most unattractive ways I
ever saw in a child. The children call her 'Mistress Mary Quite Contrary,' and
though it's naughty of them, one can't help understanding
it." "Perhaps if her mother had carried her pretty face and her pretty manners oftener into the
nursery Mary might have learned some pretty ways too. It is very sad,
now the poor beautiful thing is gone, to remember that many people never even
knew that she had a child at all." "I believe she scarcely ever looked at her SED Mrs.
Crawford. "When her a was dead there was no one to give a thought to the little
thing. Think of the servants running away and leaving her all alone in that deserted
bungalow. Colonel mcru said he nearly jumped out of his skin when he opened
the door and found her standing by herself in the middle of the
room." Mary made the long voyage to England under the care of an officer's
wife, who was taking her children to leave them in a boarding
school She was very much absorbed in her own little boy and girl, and was rather
glad to hand the child over to the woman Mr archal Craven sent to meet her, in
London. The woman was his housekeeper at mwe Manor, and her name was Mrs.
Medlock. She was a stout woman, with very red cheeks and sharp black eyes. She wore
a very purple dress, a black silk mantle with jet fringe on it and a black bonnet
with purple velvet flowers which stuck up and trembled when she moved her head.
Mary did not like her at all, but as she very seldom liked people
there was nothing remarkable in that; besides which it was very evident Mrs.
Medlock did not think much of her. "My word! she's a plain little piece
of goods!" she said. "And we'd heard that her mother was a beauty. She hasn't
handed much of it down, has she, ma'am?" "Perhaps she will improve as she grows
older," the officer's wife said good-naturedly. "If she were not so sad L
and had a nicer expression, her features are rather good. Children alter so
much." "She'll have to alter a good deal," answered Mrs. Medlock. "And there's nothing
likely to improve children at mistle if you ask me!" They thought Mary was not listening
because she was standing a little apart from them at the window of the private
hotel they had gone to. She was watching the passing buses and cabs, and people,
but she heard quite well and was made very curious about her uncle and the
place he lived in. What sort of a place was it, and what would he be
like? What was a hunchback? She had never seen one. Perhaps there were none in
India. Since she had been living in other people's houses and had had no ey she
had begun to feel lonely and to think queer thoughts which were new to her. She
had begun to wonder why she had never seemed to belong to anyone even when her
father and mother had been alive. Other children seemed to belong to
their fathers and mothers, but she had never seemed to really be anyone's little
girl. She had had servants, and food and clothes, but no one had taken any notice
of her. She did not know that this was because she was a disagreeable child; but
then, of course, she did not know she was disagreeable. She often thought that
other people were, but she did not know that she was so
herself. She thought Mrs. Medlock the most disagreeable person she had ever seen,
with her common, highly colored face and her common fine
bonnet. When the next day they set out on their journey to Yorkshire, she walked
through the station to the railway carriage with her head up and trying to
keep as far away from her as she could, because she did not want to seem to
belong to her. It would have made her very angry to think people imagined she was her little
girl. But Mrs. Medlock was not in the least disturbed by her and her
thoughts. She was the kind of woman who would "stand no nonsense from young
ones." At least, that is what she would have said if she had been
asked. She had not wanted to go to London just when her sister Maria's daughter
was going to be married, but she had a comfortable well-paid
place as housekeeper at mwe Manor and the only way in which she could keep it
was to do at once what Mr archal Craven told her to do. She never dared even to
ask a question. "Captain Lennox and his wife died of the
Cera Mr. Craven had said in his short, cold way. "Captain Lennox was my wife's brother
and I am their daughter's guardian. The child is to be brought here. You must go
to London and bring her yourself." So she packed her small trunk and made the
journey. Mary sat in her corner of the railway carriage and looked plain and
fretful. She had nothing to read or to look at, and she had folded her thin
little black gloved hands in her lap. Her black dress made her look yellower than
ever, and her limp light hair straggled from under her black crepe hat.
"A more ml looking young one I never saw in my life," Mrs. Medlock
thought m is a Yorkshire word and means spoiled and pettish.) She had never seen a child who
sat so still without doing anything; and at last she got tired of watching her
and began to talk in a brisk, hard voice. "I suppose I may as well tell you
something about where you are going to," she she said. "Do you know anything about your
uncle?" "No," said Mary. "Never heard your father and mother talk about him?" "No," said
Mary frowning. She frowned because she remembered that her father and mother
had never talked to her about anything in particular. Certainly they had never told her
things muttered Mrs. Medlock, staring at her queer, unresponsive little face. She
did not say anymore for a few moments and then she began again. "I suppose you
might as well be told something— —to prepare you. You are going to a queer
place." Mary said nothing at all, and Mrs.
Medlock looked rather discomforted by her apparent indifference, but, after taking a breath,
she went on. "Not but that it's a grand big place
in a gloomy way, and Mr. Craven's proud of it in his way— —and that's gloomy enough,
too. The house is 600 years old and it's on the edge of the mo and there's near
aund rooms in it, though most of them shut up and locked. And there's pictures
and fine old furniture and things that's been there for ages, and there's a big
park around it and gardens and trees with branches trailing to the ground—
—some of them." She paused and took another breath. "But there's nothing else," she ended
suddenly. Mary had begun to listen in spite of herself. It all sounded so
unlike India, and anything new rather attracted her. But she did not intend to
look as if she were interested. That was one of her unhappy, disagreeable ways. So she sat
still. "Well," said Mrs. Medlock. "What do you think of it?" "Nothing," she answered. "I know
nothing about such places."
That made Mrs. Medlock laugh a short sort of laughe she said, "but you are like an old
woman. Don't you care?" "It doesn't matter," said Mary, "whether I care or
not you're right enough there," said Mrs.
Medlock. "It doesn't. What you to be kept at mleth Mana for I don't know, unless
because it's the easiest way. He's not going to trouble himself about you,
that's sure and certain.
He never troubles himself about no one." She stopped herself as if she had
just remembered something in time. "He's got a crooked back," she said. "That set him
wrong. He was a sour young man and got no
good of all his money and big place till he was married." Mary's eyes turned toward her in
spite of her intention not to seem to care. She had never thought of the
hunchbacks being married and she was a trifle surprised.
Mrs. Medlock saw this, and as she was a talkative woman she continued with more
interest. This was one way of passing some of the time, at any rate. "She was a
sweet, pretty thing and he'd have walked the world over to get her a blade of grass she
wanted. Nobody thought she'd marry him, but she did, and people said she married
him for his money. But she didn't— —she didn't," positively.
"When she died—" Mary gave a little involuntary jump.
"Oh! did she die!" she exclaimed, quite without meaning to. She had just
remembered a French fairy story she had once read called RI alah hoop It had
been about a poor hunchback and a beautiful princess and it had made her
suddenly sorry for Mr archal Craven. "Yes, she died," Mrs. Medlock
answered. "And it made him queerer than ever. He cares about nobody. He won't see
people. Most of the time he goes away, and when he is at mistle he shuts himself up
in the West Wing and won't let anyone but Pitcher see him piter's an old
fellow, but he took care of him when he was a child and he knows his
ways." It sounded like something in a book and it did not make Mary feel
cheerful. A house with a hundred rooms, nearly all all shut up and with their
doors locked— —a house on the edge of a Moore whatsoever a Moore was— —sounded
dreary. A man with a crooked back who shut himself up
also! She stared out of the window with her lips pinched together, and it seemed
quite natural that the rain should have begun to pour down in Grays slanting
lines and splash and stream down the window panes If the pretty wife had been alive
she might have made things cheerful by being something like her own mother and
by running in and out and going to parties as she had done in frocks "full of
lace." But she was not there anymore You needn't expect to see him,
because 10 to one you won't," said Mrs.
Medlock. "And you mustn't expect that there will be people to talk to you.
You'll have to play about and look after yourself. You'll be told what rooms you
can go into and what rooms you're to keep out of. There's gardens enough. But
when you're in the house don't go wandering and poking about. Mr. Craven won't have
it." "I shall not want to go poking about," said sour little Mary; and just as
suddenly as she had begun to be rather sorry for Mr archal Craven she began to
cease to be sorry and to think he was unpleasant enough to deserve all that had happened to
him. And she turned her face toward the streaming Pains of the window of the
railway carriage and gazed out at the gray rainstorm which looked as if it
would go on forever and ever. She watched it so long and steadily that the
grayness grew heavier and heavier before her eyes and she fell
asleep. CHAPTER 3 ACROSS THE